Ivan Obeso Agüera - Senior backend engineer

Olaias area, Lisbon, Portugal







Profile

I hold a Bachelor's degree & MSc in Computer Science with +10 years of professional experience in **Full-stack development**. I am focusing on **backend** development although I have held some pure frontend roles in the past. I started my career working with Java technologies but in the last 5 years, I have been using **Typescript** and **Node**. My current areas of interest are Scala (**functional programming**), distributed systems, and high-performance applications. I am also very into **blockchain** development (4 years of professional experience), its possibilities for the payments industry, and its impact on society.

I am a good team player and enjoy sharing knowledge through pair programming: I believe **good communication** within the team is a crucial performance boost.

Experience

Senior backend engineer, Outplayed.com

Remote — Aug 2022 – now

I am a member of a 3 developers team supporting the infrastructure and code of the backend of outplayed.com. The backend is developed in Typescript and AWS lambdas, SQS, SNS, and DynamoDB, all handled with Terraform. My daily tasks are debugging errors, implementing some new features, and monitoring the performance of the systems via Datadog and AWS console.

It is a data-intensive application that handles thousands of users and updates prices in milliseconds. Performance on the execution time and use of resources are key here and its impact is immediately realizable in production.

Senior backend developer, Big Town Chef (Coinburp)

Remote — Aug 2021 – Aug 2022

I designed, developed, tested, and deployed backend services to support blockchain smart contracts. The backend fetches all the on-chain events emitted by our contracts and processes them, store them in a database, and exposes this data in an API to be consumed by our frontend. The focus was on functional programming, small composable functions, and being easily testable.

The period I worked here covered: the creation of the company token. creation of NFTs and minting process. Staking of tokens and NFTs. Giving backend support to run raffles, lotteries, and gifts for staking to gather engagement from the community. Tech support for collaborations with other NFT projects and integration with them. *Technologies used*: typescript, docker, jest, ava, Prisma, Postgres SQL, AWS

Senior backend developer, Wabco

Dublin, Ireland — Jan 2021 – July 2021

I worked as a backend developer in a serverless project to fetch, process, and store events from IoT devices. The software gathers information about all the devices installed in each truck of a fleet to control the vehicle. This project relied completely on AWS technologies: the application was split into lambda functions, S3, AWS IoT, AWS gateway... My role covered testing the current codebase, developing new functions, and refactoring code. *Technologies used*: Node, Typescript, Jest, Serverless, AWS Gateway, SQS, DynamoDB, Lambda.

Senior Fullstack developer, ConsenSys

Dublin, Ireland — Aug 2018 – Dec 2020

I worked as a full-stack developer in ConsenSys. My work balance between frontend and backend is 70% – 30% respectively. I am part of the development team of *Komgo* project (https://komgo.io/) a platform to trade commodities over a private blockchain based on Ethereum. My daily work includes design, the definition of user stories, and direct contact with the client in an agile environment. I have actively contributed to the design and implementation of the KYC application and the sharing and signing of documents between nodes using solidity. My role also includes mentoring and helping new members to ramp up on the team.

Technologies used: Blockchain, Ethereum, Quorum, Solidity, Ganache, Typescript, React, Redux, Jest, Docker, AWS, Kubernetes, Kaleido.

Senior backend developer, VSware

Dublin, Ireland — Sep 2017 – Jul 2018

I maintained the main module through bug fixing and new feature developments. My daily work included refactoring, cleaning code, and improving the performance of the system. **Technologies used**: VueJS, Javascript, Java, Spring, SQL

Software developer, EdgeVerve (Infosys)

Dublin, Ireland — Jul 2016 - Sep 2017

Our areas of investigation are distributed systems and blockchain. The goal of the lab is to design and develop proof-of-concept prototypes to explore new technologies to open new lines of business. *Technologies used*: Scala, Akka, Javascript, React, VueJS, NodeJS, Docker. I have actively participated in:

- Smart bond: project built on Ethereum to manage the distribution of bonds from issuers
 to investors. The system was built to be network agnostic (Quorum, OpenLedger) and
 fully scalable.
- Secure Akka: a distributed system based on CRDT to handle the creation and distribution of certificates over a non-reliable network of nodes. All the information is shared in a safe and verifiable way. Users can grant permissions to other users to access those items, and revoke them at any time.

Software engineer, BAE Systems Applied Intelligence

Dublin, Ireland — Feb 2015 – Jun 2016

Developer of *WLM* (WatchList Manager) component of *NetReveal* solution. *NetReveal* is a software package to combat fraud, intended for government departments, the finance sector, and commercial organizations.

- Bugfixing defects on the text-matching algorithms. Corrections on the match scoring methods and improvements of the performance.
- Full refactoring of some important pieces of code.
- Design and implementation of new features such as "Swift 2015 message" support.

Programmer Analyst, Nortia – Inteligencia de Negocio

Gijon, Spain — Jun 2013 - Nov 2014

I worked in the development team of *Segmentia*, an application for market segmentation in supermarkets. This tool allows marketing experts to create, manage and execute market campaigns with complex criteria regardless of the database platform they use.

My daily work included bug fixing (backend and frontend) using Groovy language & Griffon. I was responsible for the implementation of new features and testing the codebase. I automated key routines for the deployment process and provided help desk support to our clients (major supermarket chains in Spain and Portugal).

R&D in Semantic Technologies, CTIC Technological Center

Gijon, Spain — Feb 2012 - Feb 2013

Internship "Introduction to research" in R+D+i area. The research field was NLP, semantic technologies, and text mining: information retrieval, word sense disambiguation, topic modeling, automatic classification of the corpus, and automatic topic extraction.

Embedded System Developer, Ingen10

Gijon, Spain — Aug 2010 - May 2011

Part of the team developing software for electronic systems in the R&D department. Worked with ATmega and PIC microprocessors using low-level languages such as C and Assembler. I have designed and implemented desktop software for receiving measurements from potentiostat devices and representing them on a plot using Java and Swing graphical library.

Education

MSc in Computer Science. University of Oviedo (Spain)

GPA 2.216 over 4 — 2008 - 2011

Thesis: "Study and design of a prototype for managing the evolution of the competencies in a company using fuzzy logic and other methods of artificial intelligence". Graded with 9.5. (Webpage of the project https://sourceforge.net/projects/empl-prof-view/)

BSc in Computer Science. University of Oviedo (Spain)

GPA 2.242 over 4 — 2004 - 2008

Specialist: "Systems administration" and "Internet applications integration" Thesis: "Web application – Automata simulator in Struts 2". Graded with 9.

Skills

Java 7, Typescript, JS (5/5)	Scala, C (4/5)	C++, Python (3/5)
J2EE, Struts, Spring, Hibernate, NodeJS, NestJS, Serverless		BACK-END
VueJS, React, Express, Storybook, Material Design		FRONT-END
Microservices, AWS, Postman, AWS Lambda		ARCHITECTURE
AKKA, Blockchain, Ethereum, Quorum, Bitcoin		
Docker, Docker Swarm, git, Maven, Kubernetes, Jenkins		CI/CD
SQL (Oracle, MySQL, SQLServer), NoSQL (Mongo, DynamoDB)		DDBB
JBoss, Tomcat, Jetty		
JUnit, DBUnit, Mockito, Spock, Selenium, JProfile, Jest, ava		TESTING
Jira, Confluence, Crucible,		
Mahout, Lucene, Weka		TEXT-MINING
Arduino, VHDL, FPGA, Quartus IDE, PIC & ATmega microcontrollers		
Agile, Scrum, TDD, BDD		METHOD.